<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="chapter_using">
    <title>Sniffing your SIM</title>

    <section id="hw_setup">
        <title>Connecting your device</title>
        <para>You will need to put your SIM into the SIMtrace hardware, connect
        one of the four flex cables to the SIMtrace hardware, put the other side
        into the SIM socket of your phone. Use USB to connect the SIMtrace hardware
        to the PC. On your PC you should be able to see the USB device now.</para>

        <figure><title>Connecting the SIMtrace Hardware</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/simtrace_hw_setup.png" width="15cm"/>
          </imageobject>
          <textobject><phrase>SIMtrace being connected</phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>
        </figure>
    </section>

    <section id="launching_simtrace">
        <title>Launching SIMtrace</title>
        <screen>
$ <command>./simtrace</command>
simtrace - GSM SIM and smartcard tracing
(C) 2010 by Harald Welte &lt;laforge@gnumonks.org&gt;
        </screen>
        <para>Launching the <command>simtrace</command> will try to find
        the SIMtrace hardware and then try to claim the USB device. The
        application will send the received data encapsulated in the GSMTAP
        format on localhost and the IANA assigned GSMTAP port.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="launching_wireshark">
        <title>Launching Wireshark</title>
        <para>The <command>wireshark</command> application will start a GUI
        and given the right permissions you should be able listen to the
        localhost interface and filter for the GSMTAP port on 4729. You should
        be able to see the decoded messages like in the figure below.</para>

         <figure><title>GSMTAP in Wireshark</title>
         <mediaobject>
           <imageobject>
             <imagedata fileref="images/wireshark-sim.png" width="16cm"/>
           </imageobject>
           <textobject><phrase>SIMtrace sending data</phrase></textobject>
         </mediaobject>
         </figure>
    </section>

    <section id="known_firmware_issues">
        <title>Known Firmware Issues</title>
        <para>The current firmware has two known bugs that limit the usage
        of the device. The first one is with enumeration on USB 3.0 controllers
        and the second one with baudrate selection of some SIM cards.</para>

        <para>The firmware does not properly enumerate on systems with USB 3.0
        controllers. The issue has not been analyzed and the workaround is to
        use a USB &lt; 3.0 port or put a USB &lt; 3.0 hub between.</para>

        <para>The firmware has issues with selecting the right baudrate of
        some SIMcards. The microcontroller will call the parity error interrupt
        handler and the watchdog will reset the device. There is no workaround
        for this issue yet.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
