<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="chapter_sniff">
    <title>Sniffing your SIM</title>

    <section id="hw_setup">
        <title>Connecting your device</title>
        <para>You will need to put your SIM into the SIMtrace hardware, connect
        one of the four flex cables to the SIMtrace hardware, put the other side
        into the SIM socket of your phone. Use USB to connect the SIMtrace hardware
        to the PC. On your PC you should be able to see the USB device now.</para>

        <figure><title>Connecting the SIMtrace Hardware</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/simtrace_hw_setup.png" width="15cm"/>
          </imageobject>
          <textobject><phrase>SIMtrace being connected</phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>
        </figure>
    </section>

    <section id="launching_simtrace">
        <title>Launching SIMtrace</title>
        <screen>
$ <command>./simtrace</command>
simtrace - GSM SIM and smartcard tracing
(C) 2010 by Harald Welte &lt;laforge@gnumonks.org&gt;
        </screen>
        <para>Launching the <command>simtrace</command> will try to find
        the SIMtrace hardware and then try to claim the USB device. The
        application will send the received data encapsulated in the GSMTAP
        format on localhost and the IANA assigned GSMTAP port.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="launching_wireshark">
        <title>Launching Wireshark</title>
        <para>The <command>wireshark</command> application will start a GUI
        and given the right permissions you should be able listen to the
        localhost interface and filter for the GSMTAP port on 4729. You should
        be able to see the decoded messages like in the figure below.</para>

         <figure><title>GSMTAP in Wireshark</title>
         <mediaobject>
           <imageobject>
             <imagedata fileref="images/wireshark-sim.png" width="16cm"/>
           </imageobject>
           <textobject><phrase>SIMtrace sending data</phrase></textobject>
         </mediaobject>
         </figure>
    </section>

    <section id="known_firmware_issues">
        <title>Known Firmware Issues</title>
        <para>For some SIM Cards the ATR and the first APDU are sent in the
        same USB message and the host utility fails to split the APDUs
        properly. A band-aid for the firmware exists.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="other_modes">
        <title>Other modes</title>
        <para>The hardware is capable to be used as an ordinary card reader,
        provide Man-In-The-Middle (MITM) attacks, or operate as a SIM. The
        firmware currently does not have support for these modes.</para>

        <para>The SIMtrace hardware supports ISO7816 Part 3  T=0/T=1 protocols,
        it basically can be used to intercept and analyze any traffic from (ISO7816)
        smart cards. This includes SIM cards, Pay TV cards (smart card for CAM),
        ATM cards, chip credit card, PKI smart cards, e-passport etc. etc. However
        watch out: You have to make your chip card fitting in the "SIM card size"
        ID-000 reader or build another adapter.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
